Before we get into the course objectives,
I want to take you through two tools you will
need to install so that you can follow along
with what you see in this course.
The downloads and installations are pretty
straightforward, but know that what you will
see on the websites I am about to show you
now may differ from what you will end up seeing,
as these tools get updated fairly frequently.
First, you will need the Python engine.
While it does come with some development tools,
the best way to ensure you have the engine
is to download it straight from the source,
python.org.
I am on the site now and will select the latest
version of Python to download.
Your operating system will dictate which version
you download, but I downloaded and installed
the Windows Installer 64-bit version as I
am running Windows 11.
Once that installation is complete, you will
need an Integrated Development Environment
app, which is a tool that supports one or
multiple programming languages.
PyCharm is a leading Python IDE, but I will
use Visual Studio code for this course, which
can be downloaded here.
I use this tool because it supports all the
programming and markup languages covered in
the IT Specialist programming certification
courses, such as this course, HTML, CSS, JavaScript,
Java, and C#, for software development fundamentals.
You can take the default installation once
you have installed the Python engine.
How do you know Python is installed correctly?
I’m glad you asked.
To verify that Python is installed, open a
command prompt, as I am doing here, and then
type py and select the Enter key on the keyboard.
If you see three arrows and some Python information,
Python is installed and ready to be used.
Holding down the Ctrl key, selecting Z, and
then selecting the Enter key on the keyboard
closes the Python session within the command
prompt.
Here is what Visual Studio Code looks like
once it is installed.
The next step is installing the Python extension,
making writing, editing, and running Python
code easier.
I will select the gear icon in the lower-left
corner of the screen, select Extensions, and
search for Python.
I already have the extension installed, but
if you don’t, select Install to install
the extension and then restart Visual Studio
Code if necessary.
One of the main benefits of the extension
is Intellisense, which helps us to write code
but also provides useful visual indicators
for any code that might contain syntax errors
and, thus, will not run correctly.
As we go through each domain, a student folder
with practice files for each domain is accessible.
To open a folder for a domain, we just need
to select File, Open Folder, select the folder
we want to open, and then choose Select Folder
to open that folder, as I am doing with the
Domain 1 student files.
Once you have completed these installations,
you can start learning and building with Python.